Hello, welcome everyone. We are in
active inference guest stream
82.5 on April 14th, 2025 discussing
computers, meaning and consciousness
with Robert Bordon and guests and
guests. So, Robert, thank you for
joining and for assembling this group to
you to kick off this
discussion. Thank you. Hi, thanks
everybody for attending. Um, I'm going
to be talking as it says on computers,
meaning and
consciousness. Um, let me get straight
into it. What I'm going to be talking
about is largely negative results. And
here are the two key negative results of
this talk. One is that the information
inside a
computer doesn't define what the
computing computation is about. And that
is because information in a computer is
encoded. And the second negative result
is that if the brain is only a computer,
if it's thought of as only a computer,
then it cannot be conscious. So those
are two quite paradoxical results and I
expect you to be puzzled by them.
Um, as I go through, I I would really be
grateful if people would put up their
hands at any time. And if there's
something that's really perplexing about
it, ask a question because very much my
purpose is to find out what people don't
understand about these results. And what
I think the argument to these results is
fairly simple arguments, but it's it's
paradoxical and
counterintuitive. and I I expect people
to be puzzled and I would like people to
speak up when they are puzzled. Okay, so
those are the negative results I'm going
to be talking about. Um, and this is one
way to remember them. It's like an
incompleteness theorem for computers.
And what it says is the physical events
inside a computer don't define what it
computes. They don't define what it's
about.
And this as I say is because the
information is encoded expert external
information is required in order to
interpret or decode the physical events
in a computer as a
computation. So that's basically what
it's about an incompleteness theorem a
negative result. I think as an
incompleteness theorem it can be quite
important. However, I've got another
slide here. So basically to try and
understand the results. The first result
is is not original result is that
computation itself is not a physical
process in itself. It is our
interpretation of a physical process. An
interpretation but made by an external
interpreter usually people but sometimes
not people using a decoding of the
physical events in the computer. And the
information running inside a computer is
encoded. So it doesn't of itself have
meaning until you decode it. And without
decoding the physical events inside a
computer don't have meaning and they're
not actually about anything. And the
puzzle here is that consciousness is
about things whereas the things in a
computer are not about things. Now this
result that computation is not a
physical process but an interpretation
of physical process that's not a new
result.
It was derived by horseman Ital in
2014 for artificial computers and
extended to natural computers such as
brains by Stephen and Kendon in
subsequent years. So those two papers
are very interesting precedents to the
work here. So that's the first part of
it is that computers don't have in
decoded meaning inside them. The second
part is applying that to consciousness
because consciousness that we experience
has meaning. It's it's about things.
It's about the things in front of us,
the things we see, the things we feel
and so on. But without com decoding, the
computation in a brain doesn't have
meaning. And the decoding requires
information from outside the brain. So
if you model the brain purely as a
computer, then the physical events
inside the brain don't have meaning. And
so they don't they can't be the cause of
consciousness. So that is the basic
framework for the
results. Uh it's a negative result. They
are negative results. And I think
negative results are important in
science. There are a lot of precedents
like conservation of energy is if you
like a negative result says energy can't
be created out of nowhere. So it leads
to things like no perpetual motion
machines. Well, the second law of
thermodynamics says you can't create
heat differences out of nothing. And so
there's no such thing as a free heat
engine. Or another one more recent is
Girdle's incompleteness theorem for
mathematics. And that says you can't
derive all of mathematic purely
aimatically. So these are important
negative results. And what negative
results do is they clear the ground and
make new for room for new ideas. So the
result of this talk is an incompleteness
theorem for computers. Excuse me a
bit. And I hope to show you that the
result has farreaching
implications firstly for man-made
computers and secondly for cognitive
science. And so if you see if you think
you see a flaw in this argument, please
put your hand up and ask me about it
because that's the kind of thing I want
to understand
about. So I'll proceed by a series of
analogies going from books to computers
to brains. These are all physical
devices and inside the devices inside a
book or inside a computer all the
information is physically encoded.
And without decoding the information has
no meaning and the decoding is always
done outside the device. So a
consequence of that is the device itself
is not conscious. Now that feels all
right for books, feels a bit more
troubling for computers and very
troubling for brains. Um anyway, let's
set off down this journey and see how
far we go.
Inside each of the
devices, the information in the device
has no meaning. It's quite obvious for a
book
that words, characters inside a book
have no meaning, but it becomes less
obvious for computers and for brains.
So, let's go through that progression
and see how we
go.
So, yes, I just have a question to be
sure. What is the ground to assert that
within the brain bearing in mind that
actually we do not understand the brain
very well at this point there is no
encoding and decoding mechanism of sort
well I think the modern view is
that there is encoding and decoding but
it doesn't happen inside the brain in
other words The sense organs encode
things like light as pulse trains,
neural spike trains. They go into the
brain as encoded information. Then the
brain does something with them. Lots of
things about neuron spike trains. And
then spike trains come out of the brain
and they are decoded as muscle actions.
So the picture of the brain has encoding
and decoding but it doesn't actually
happen in the brain. It happens in the
body in the sense organs or in the
muscles.
I think it's a something that could be
discussed. Uh bearing in mind again that
there are probably fundamental mechanism
within the brain we do not yet fully
understand. Oh yes, a lot. Okay, let's
assume it's a post too late. Okay. More
than something that is
uh well I I think it's I think I can
assume that any information is the in
the brain is encoded. We we know all we
find in the brain is neural spike trains
and if that is information about the
world, it's certainly
encoded. Anyway, let's go from books to
computers to brains and then we'll see
how it feels. So in a book there are
physical squirrels on the page as shown
here and we do a lot of interpreting of
those in order to understand the book.
We understand the shapes of the ink
shapes as letters. We understand strings
of letters as words and word strings as
sentences, sentences as meanings and
meanings as stories. So finally after
all that interpretation, all that
decoding, we understand what the meaning
is in the book. But to get the meaning
from the book, we've had to do a lot of
decoding. By the way, I shall use the
word interpret and the word decode
fairly interchangeably throughout this
talk. And I think um they obviously
don't have entirely the same meaning,
but I think they're pretty synonymous
for these purposes. But you may want to
catch me up on that sometimes and say,
"Look, you've used these words
differently." So that's what meaning is
in books. It's not physically inside the
book. It's inside our heads when we read
the
book. So we go on from books to
computers. And physically, what's going
on inside a computer is digital
electronics. We understand the laws of
physics and how all that stuff, all
those circuits work. But again to
understand it as a computer we do a lot
of interpretation. We interpret the
voltages on in the circuit as bits. We
interpret bit strings as numbers. We
interpret numbers as being solutions to
equations or how whatever we've done.
And we pro sometimes interpret those
equations and models of physical things.
We have computer a simulation of
anything in the world. And that's the
way we understand it by doing all that
decoding all that chain of decoding. So
when we do that there's a lot of
decoding information in our heads which
I say is not inside the computer. The
computer just has physical digital
electronics. So we go further to brains.
Physically what happens in brains is
neurons firing and as I say what what
has started those neurons firing is
sense organs like eyes and fingers
sending spike trains to the brain
recording
um information about the world but that
information encoded as spike trains.
Then the spike trains
uh interpreted in the brain in various
way are used as we interpret the brain
as a computer doing basian probability
for instance. So we may think that the
spike trains in the brain have a meaning
as probabilities of things and
probabilities of
events and we interpret synaptic
connection strength in the brain as
learning and memory. And then spike
trains come out of the brain to our
muscles and our muscles decode the spike
trains as motor actions. So again there
is encoding before stuff goes into the
brain. Stuff I inside the brain is
encoded and then there's decoding when
it comes out of the brain.
So those are the three
devices and to sort of draw the
generalization across those in all three
cases there a chain of interpretations
there's a chain of decoding which says
we decode A as B as B as C as C as D and
so on we decode voltages as bits bits as
numbers numbers as solutions to
equations whatever it may be or numbers
as being about
things. And at each link of this
decoding chain, there is various very
many possibles. There's no one obvious
choice. There's a vast number of
possible interpretations. And when we do
this interpretation, it's us decoding
and we need information to do that
decoding. We need to know things about
how computers work or things about how
the brain works or things about what
problem we set the computer. And so
that's how we set up our
interpretations. But there's a huge
number of wrong interpretations we could
set up instead. But the important point
is the information we use to decode
resides outside the device. And that
means that there may be information
inside the device, but it doesn't have
the meaning that we apply to it. And
that the consequence of that I would
say is that the device
itself is not conscious. And so we've
gone through this progression from books
to computers to
brains. And the question is is there
anywhere along that trail where
something different
happened? And I claim there's not
anywhere that something different
happened. The the whole issue of code
encoding and decoding is the same for
all three of those devices.
So an example of a computer is a floor
cleaning robot. Now you know how these
work. Initially it blunders around the
room and bumps into doors and
things and it's been designed with an
onboard computer which has a a digital
map of the room with things in it and
representation of things like chairs and
tables and so on.
And so once it's bumped into a table, it
doesn't bump into the table again. And
so it has the map inside it which is
encoded information. And the decoding of
that information happens outside the
computer when the computer sends
commands to the motor and to the
steering to avoid the table leg. And the
decoding also happens in the designer's
mind where the designer has he knows
what the memory locations in the
computer mean. But there's no
information in the computer which
defines what the information means. In
other words, it's got a bunch of memory
locations. But it doesn't know which
memory locations refer to particular
objects in the outside world or
particular
places. So the computer on the robot
can't look at its memory locations to be
aware of the table leg.
And this is illustrating the general
point that the physical events inside
the computer don't define what it's
computing
about. And I think one of the reasons
people find that puzzling is that when
people talk about computers, they use a
lot of metaphors. And even the word
computer is a metaphor for people. And
these metaphors make computers sound
like people. And those are the metaphors
that I think have misled us and made
this sound puzzling to many of us.
Um, well, where do we go next? Another
simple example of a kind of computer is
an
abacus. Now, there's an abacus. And what
happens inside an abacus, I think most
people would say, is not addition. The
physical process inside an ab aocus is
beads sliding along wires. But we've
designed the abacus so we can interpret
it as an adding
machine. So in some bizaar in the Middle
East or something you see somebody doing
things on an abacus he is adding up
numbers money basically. Now that's the
way we interpret the abacus as a
computer which does additions but we
could interpret the same physical device
in many different ways. We could have
used it as a model of sheep in the
meadow or we could have used it as a
model of fish on the moon. We could have
used it for fortuneelling or we could
have used it for multiplying. I'll just
talk about multiplying briefly. If you
imagine those red beads as being digits
in a number like
10,000 1 0 0 0 every time you move a
bead over to the right hand side you're
multiplying the number on the right hand
side by factor 10. So in that sense if
we used abacuses that way they would be
multiplying devices not adding devices.
So again the physical events that happen
inside the abacus don't define what
computation is going on. It's people
that encode the inputs and decode the
outputs. And in terms of the previous
analysis of computers from horsemen and
stemian company people are called
representing entities who interpret the
abacus as an adding machine. They do the
encoding and they do the decode.
So the first set of consequences of this
viewpoint are consequences for man-made
computers and particularly artificial
intelligence. And the first consequence
is you may have heard there's quite a
popular idea around amongst philosophers
and others that we might be living
inside a simulation. In other words,
there might be some grand simulation of
the universe which simulates everything,
the world and people and things and we
are just existing inside it. Now, this
interpretation of computers shows that's
not the case. In other words, if you
have a big simulating computer, the
information inside it is encoded. Sorry,
I can't quite read some of the my slides
because the picture in front of it. But
uh so the simulated things don't exist
inside the computer. They exist inside
the heads of the people looking at the
computer outputs. And so there are no
simulated people inside a computer. So
we cannot be simulated
people. A second consequence which again
is quite topical. There's a lot of
discussion about AI advancing and
becoming more intelligence. And there's
the idea of AI super intelligence which
completely exceeds all human
intelligence. Again, if you take this
interpreted view of computers, that
can't happen
because inside an AI computer, any
computer doing AI, there is only digital
electronics.
There's not meaning about things. All
the intelligence in AI computer is
encoded information and it takes people
to decode
it. And so when we talk about AI, all
the intelligence lies not inside the
machine but in human interpretation of
the outputs. And as an example of this,
Deep Blue played wonderful chess. Um,
but it only played great chess because
Gary Kasparov thinks it played great
chess. Another more humble example, um,
you may have heard the old wartime
computer called Eniac, which was very
good at printing log log tables. It
could print log tables much better than
people could print log
tables. But it only printed great log
tables because people were able to read
them and say, "Yes, these are great log
tables."
So if an AI computer does something
which you might want to call super
intelligence, produces outputs that
nobody can understand because it's
beyond all human intelligence. It's
actually not intelligence at all. It's
not intelligence until humans interpret
it. It's just
electronics. Now these two results are
quite against the tide of what a lot of
people believe. The way to remember
them is that inside a computer there is
no decoding. So there's no the the
decoding is needed to make meaningful
information and therefore people
simulated people and AI super
intelligence do not exist inside
computers.
So um to go back to the analysis which
was the origin of this horseman in 2014
showed that computing is not just a
physical process. It's an interpretation
of a physical
process by something they call a
representational entity an here. Now the
re is the thing that encodes the inputs
to the computer and decodes the outputs.
And the important thing to know is that
the information used by the re to decode
resides in the re itself not inside the
computer. And so this applies firstly
they applied this to man-made computers
because that's their interest. But they
extend it then to artificial to
biological computers. And in this case,
the representational entity which
interprets the brain as a computer is
the animal's body because it's the sense
organs that encode the information on
the way in and his motor actions,
muscles which decode the information on
the way out. And again, we get this
result applying to brains. The physical
events inside a brain don't define what
it's computing
about. Okay. Um
yeah, just a question. Uh I think I
understand where you're coming from when
you state that the body is the decoder
or is where decoding of neural
information is enacted.
But uh I think it's also a huge uh
assumption. Uh and I would uh for
instance ask you what you think happens
when we have a reminiscence when we
recall something from memory and it's
very vivid for instance or like in
dreams or in imagination where we may
imagine ourself moving as a body in
space. Sure. But the body is not
actually that's something we could
discuss in the fine details. But well
that where I'm going is that most
theories of consciousness and the brain
see the brain as only a computer. And
what I'm saying is if the brain is only
a computer there information inside it
can't have meaning and there cannot be
consciousness. What I'm going to say is
the brain is more than just a computer.
There's something else in the brain
besides a computer and I'll come to what
that is and that is the thing that is
conscious when we have memories or when
we make plans or imagine things or
whatever else it might be. Okay. So
that's where I'm going that the the
brain is is a computer but it's not only
a computer. There's something else in
there.
Okay.
So, thank you. Yeah.
Um, just I should have started by
apologizing. I have to go to a TMBB
meeting in a few minutes, but um I think
it's a fascinating um argument. I just
wanted to put a question um that I'm
hoping you can come back to later on. Um
again acknowledging I think these you
know this is a really interesting
approach and I suspect you're absolutely
right. Um, however, at the back of my
mind, I'm wondering how many of these
philosophical arguments have
accommodated the pre-energy principle
that is just the statement that any
physical process is just a process of
computation in the sense of belief
updating. So that all the internal
elements of your brain and a computer
that can be read as a process as opposed
to a book or an abacus which is not a
process can be read as belief updating.
basically whose physics move on a
statistical manifold and just by using
those kinds of semantics and uh trans
translating things like interpretation,
decoding, observation, measurement,
these are just processes of inference.
In that reading of physical
processes, you have meaning baked in. So
the whole point of the free energy
principle is that the physical process
encodes or has stands in for a
parameterization of beliefs about
something. There is an inherent
intrinsic meaning that is equipped or
equipss all the physical processes in
virtue of the free principle because you
can distinguish the physical process
from the support of the beliefs entailed
by that physical process about things
that are not that physical process. So
that's the whole point of the mark of
blanket that now you have an
information the theory an information
geometry that allows you to have beliefs
about things which are just meaning. So
my question is how much of this
philosophical work and and you know can
you apply the second law or girdle's
theorem um to um open systems that have
a distinction between the encoding of
beliefs by the the inside
about the outside. So that would be my
challenge. Oh I've still got two minutes
left to to to to witter but I'm not. I'm
going to listen to Brianna's question.
Thank you Carl. It's a very profound
question and I do come to it some of it
later but I'll try to address it
properly later.
Hi uh thanks for having me here and um
it's a fascinating argument. I'm uh
curious about the comments on AI. Um so
AI runs on an emulated substrate so it's
um it's remarkably similar to how it
works in human cognition. And I wonder
if we're not taking into consideration
that it's um the substrate is emulated.
Um I think the argument I mean AI is
complicated because it runs on digital
computers. are doing digital electronics
and bits and bites and they are usually
simulating neural nets and the neural
nets are something like what the brain
works and so it's a very complicated
situation but
fundamentally there is still at the
bottom level a lot of encoding going on
and a lot of decoding is needed to make
any sense of it. Um so it it that's a
question that leads in a lot of
directions but fundamentally there is
always encoding and decoding is always
required.
There is and it would be on top of the
um the emulated substrate which just
yeah you have to decode levels. You have
to decode the bits and byes as um as
simulating a neural net. You have to
decode the neural net as producing
conclusions. So there are many level
usually in computers there are many many
levels of virtual machine going on and
many levels of decoding you have to do
to get to the
meaning. All I need is one level of
decoding. That's enough. Sure.
Well that's my question or my remark.
So I I carry on.
Um so now we're coming on to brains and
consciousness and we take three
statements which I think
are fairly widely believed. One is that
consciousness is caused by events inside
the
brain. Number two is that consciousness
has meanings about external things like
coffee cups or the presentation or your
computer screen.
And the third point is that the brain is
a neural computer and only a neural
computer. Now these statements I will
claim are not mutually consistent. One
of them has to be wrong. And the reason
is if the brain is only a neural
computer. All the information inside is
encoded and has no defined meaning. So
that information can't cause
consciousness of things. consciousness
with meanings inside it. And if you look
at those three statements, the first two
I think are empirical facts and we can
come back to discuss that later. But
most people believe that consciousness
is caused by events in the brain because
when brains are damaged, consciousness
gets interrupted and you can't be
conscious. Most of the things you're
conscious of are um something happening
in the brain and it has meaning about
external things. I think those two are
well established facts. So the third is
an assumption. We're only assuming that
the computing is the only thing that
goes on in brain. So I think three is
the thing that's
wrong. Now where do um so that runs
straight up against a computer a a uh a
philosophical um assumption called
computational functionalism.
Computational function is a thesis that
performing the right kind of
computations is is sufficient necessary
and sufficient for consciousness and
this is described recently as a
mainstream although disputed position in
the philosophy of
mind. Now it's also called computational
sufficiency. David Char has called it
that an article in 2012. And what the
results of the first half of this talk
imply is that that is wrong. In other
words, being a computer is not
sufficient to be
conscious. Now, most theories of
consciousness assume computational
functionalism. They are theories in
which the brain is a computer and the
brain has consciousness by virtue of
being a computer. So the implication of
this viewpoint is that those theories of
consciousness cannot be correct and that
is the main implication of this talk for
theories of
consciousness. So um to talk about some
specific theories of consciousness most
of them assume that consciousness is
caused by events of the brain. The brain
is a complicated neural computer most
complicated machine in the universe we
see here. And inside this computer there
are various comput computational
processes taking place and I call these
P1, P2 and so on. And most theories of
consciousness assume that one or other
of these processes called P5 or P4
causes consciousness. And so you can
look at examples of modern theories of
consciousness
uh from this viewpoint. Uh you might
think P1 is representing things in the
visual field and uh theories of
consciousness like lame like um yeah
lame and so on. Uh people believe those
theories or you might think as in the
free energy principle that the brain is
building basian models of reality and
that lead to consciousness. Or you might
feel some higher order theory of
consciousness that P3 is the brain
reflecting on its own computations and
that causes
consciousness. Or going with Antonio
Damasio, you might feel that the brain
is computing an emotional response to
events and that emotional response is
the heart of consciousness. Or you might
feel along with Bernard Bars and Deain
and others that global workspace is what
makes us conscious. So making
information globally available is a
computational process or you might feel
along with IIT that you need computation
linked together with some very high
connectivity which this measure five or
you might think that P7 is predictive
coding all of those you're saying
some computational process is what makes
the brain
conscious the point of this talk is that
Those processes P1 or P2 or whatever
they are don't happen inside brains.
They happen in our interpretations of
brains as computations but from the
information actually inside a brain
itself. The processes could be
completely different processes. They
could be Q1, Q2 and so on. And so those
theories of consciousness cannot work.
And if you want a short code monmonic
for why those theories of consciousness
cannot be right, it is those theories of
consciousness treat the brain as a
computer. So they have encoding but they
don't have
decoding. And so they can't get
consciousness has decoded meaning in it.
And so a theory which only has encoding
but no decoding can't get decoded
meaning. And we go back again now to the
example of a floor cleaning robot just
to illustrate what that means.
Supposing in a floor cleaning robot, we
can go and talk to the designer or read
the design handbook and get a complete
theory of how the how the robot computer
works. Supposing we've done that for
brains. Supposing we have a complete
model of all the neurons in the brain,
what they're doing. And so we happen to
know that a particular confidential
process called visual perception is
implemented by certain neurons we can
point at in the brain neurons N1 N2 and
so on or there's some higher another
process higher order computing that's
done by a different set of
neurons and you can divide that set you
can say the higher order computing about
an object B is done by process P4B and
that is done by certain neurons ones
which we've identified called N4B and
and so on and so forth. And so there we
are. We've made great progress at
cognitive science understanding how the
brain works and now we propose a theory
of consciousness. So we say the
consciousness of object B in our visual
field is caused by process
P4B. So what form would that theory
take? What we're saying is information
physically inside the brain including
the information in neural events N3B and
the particular neurons causes awareness
of object B. But this theory is not
possible because information inside the
brain doesn't define which neurons are
the group
N3B inside the brain is not known which
are neurons N3B. There might be any
neurons. So, and the information to
decode N3B as the process P3B doesn't
exist inside the brain. And so, there's
no possible theory in which
consciousness arises from physical
events inside the brain. To go back to
the Roomba example, the robot example,
the robot has memory with load of memory
locations, one of which represents a
table leg, but it doesn't, the robot
itself doesn't know which memory
location represents the table leg. So
the robot itself cannot be conscious of
the table leg. And it's an exact
parallel I claim between those two
cases.
So um I would like to pause at this
point ask people to chip in with
questions doubts and so on. Um I'll just
restraate the incompleteness theorem.
The physical events inside a computer
don't define what it computes and that
external information is required to
interpret those events as a computation
and to give them any meaning. So few
questions for you. Is this a correct
viewpoint of computation? Is it just a
physical process or does it require an
external interpreter or
decoder? And do modern theories of
consciousness have any decoding built
into them? Or if they don't, what does
it imply for those theories? So I will
pause and anybody wants to put their
hands up
or come up with objections.
Yeah. Kenneth and anyone else?
Yeah, thanks Robert. I mean I I think
um you know I was reminded when I was
looking at your slides uh earlier and
then now again
that this was all
debated for a long time actually um in
the late in the late 80s. That's right
in the early 90s part kind of famously
by John Surl and Daniel Dennett. So Surl
on one side and Denn on the other. Um
you know Surl kind of in a way made most
of his or a big chunk of his philos
philosophical career just going around
giving the Chinese room argument.
Absolutely. Yeah. Um and Dennett I mean
in a way Dennett's response was
something it
was you know it was kind of unclear but
it sort of bordered on illusionism some
of the time. Um yeah and then sometimes
a kind of incoherent position where it
seemed to presuppose that you could take
the intent what Dennett called the
intentional stance which is say to
interpret entities as exhibiting
intentionality. So for SURL, you know,
the vacuum cleaning uh computer robot,
the vacuum cleaning robot, it's it's as
if it wants to, you know, vacuum stuff
and make a map of the room, but it
doesn't literally do it. It just sort of
has a structure that's sufficient for us
to go, oh, it it's as if it maps the
room, but it doesn't literally map the
room, right? And and of course, Denned
wanted to um either say that all
intentionality is all is as if
intentionality and and that as if
intentionality meant adopting the
intentional stance and interpreting an
entity as if it had intentionality. So
then if you apply that apply that to
yourself, what is your interpreting
activity? Is it intentional or not? So
then it does the kind of the
incoherence. I'm not as if. I mean I
know I'm not as if. Yes. Of course,
Dennett would say, "Oh, no, you don't
know that."
Right. So, well, I Yeah. Yeah. That
those I mean those questions are very
important questions and I would go back
even further than John C to Livveness
the Livess
Mills inside the mill. Do they know
anything about the wind sort of thing?
Sure. But John Cell made the Chinese
room argument that said computers can't
have meaning inside them. And to my
mind, nobody produced a satisfactory
answer. Yeah, I agree with you on that.
I've I've always thought that. I think
like there was a lot of debate about it.
Uh it lasted to about the mid 90s and
then people just quit talking about it.
Well, also David
Yeah. I mean, I think David Charas came
back to it in about the 2000s. He said
computation is a a causal network or
causal topology and that has meaning. I
think his answer was unsatisfactory but
we could talk about that. But I think
basically nobody's really answered John
C and the conclusion that I'm reaching
is that it agrees with John S that you
need something else besides computers
going on to get consciousness. I I see
that. And then then there's also you
know those old sort of famous results in
mathematical logic. I mean other than
girls incompleteness thems
where you can have you know non-standard
models of um domains where it's like
just a first order you know model of
even arithmetic doesn't really capture
arithmetic you know. Yeah sure. No,
I it requires a kind of oh, we're going
to interpret it as just being this and
then I may have gotten that one wrong,
but there results like that. And then
there's the whole issue of the um
non-catategoricity of first order uh
models. So second order, but we don't
have a good idea of how to compute
second order models to get categoricity.
Um no no my views on mathematics are
unpopular. I I would say mathematics I
everybody sees mathematics as this
separate abstract domain. Actually I
think certain elementary facts of
mathematics like 2 plus 2 equal four.
They're about numbers. They're not
abstract and they are experimental facts
and they agree with the data. When you
have two things and add two things, you
get four things. And we learned that.
Yeah. But I I thought, you know, in
terms the only alternative a
computationalist has here is to say
something like there are objective facts
uh that pertain to say what a
computation what a realized computation
computes that are kind of intrinsic to
it. And that's almost exactly. Yeah.
That's almost a kind of Pythagorean
position you would have to hold. Well, I
I think that is is straightforwardly
wrong. In other words, I can have a
computation
uh like a logical and gate. I can have
two ones make a one. But I can interpret
that either as an andgate or if I
interpret if I change around and say no,
one means true and false and and not
means true. I can say no, it's not an
andgate. not doing and it's doing all or
again in terms of bitwise
operations I can say this operation on
bits in the computer is addition or I
can say no I haven't represented used
bits represent 1 2 3 4 I've used bits to
represent 1 10 100 a thousand so the
operation is actually doing is
multiplication and so there is no
objective fact about what operation what
computation
is doing. Yeah. I mean, if you think
that, then I think you're right. So, I'
I've often thought this that what the
computationalist has to say is that no,
there are objective facts about what
certain realized computational
structures compute. And maybe was Carl
saying something like that before he got
about the the free energy? I think he
was. Yeah.
It's a shame because I've got uh slides
coming up about 3 in principle and
markoff blankets and so on. We could
have discussed them then. But uh anyway,
I'll get to discuss that with Carl later
cuz I'm giving this talk to the TNB
later. So, but um I think Carl was sort
of saying that there is an
interpretation a unique interpretation
of a
computation and I think there are just
too many counter examples. I think any
computation you show me, I can and you
show me your interpretation of it, I can
show you another interpretation that's
just as
good.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, when you said, if I
may say one last thing, when you when
you talked about and Davidid mentioned
this,
um, the sensory and motor
encoding as a kind of locus of real
representational content. Is that how I
Yeah. Um, yeah. Sensor organs encode and
mo muscles decode. Okay. Why couldn't
somebody raise the same objection that
you're raising to computation as
encoding meaning to that
process? Um because there again you
might say well it depend even you know
to kind of look at another line of uh
theory of intentionality theory of
meaning theory of representation that
went on around the same time there's for
example Ruth Milikin's sort of
naturalistic theory that would allow you
to assign a definite content to sensory
and motor you know encoding and decoding
but it's all kind of based on
evolutionary history. Um, and if the
evolutionary history were different, but
you had exactly the same physical
inputs, outputs, and so on, you would
get a different content. And that's kind
of
um an unsat to my way of thinking kind
of unsatis for it may be fine with
respect to like what the body is
objectively doing and what it evolved
for but um in terms of conscious content
it seems to me it's it's not going to
work. It's too externalist. Makes it
like even if I had a completely
different evolution and you know but I
ended up being this kind of atom for
Adam replica of what I am now. The
contents of my thoughts don't really
change. It seems to me well yeah I mean
I would say you can't throw evolution
away like that or you can't play with it
like that. I think the brain is a result
of evolution and evolution has meant
that sense organs have evolved to encode
light and touch and so on and muscles
have evolved to do things and brains
have evolved to make sure that they do
the right things and all that is is a
coherent picture and I cannot just pull
that apart basically.
So you, if I understand you, you you you
might you you would you think that you
can't play the same objection to the
representational content of sensory
uh sensory encoding and motor decoding,
however you want to think of it. Well, I
think as you can play it, step back a
bit. I think all the theories we
have in natural science or gas laws or
whatever it might be involve encoding
and
decoding. And the theory we have of the
brain involves encoding by sense organs,
involves decoding by muscles. And so
that is that theory is a coherent
package that we can test against data on
its own. Whereas the difficulty with
consciousness is that we don't see the
decoding. Whereas we know that
consciousness it is about decoded
information. Yeah. But ordinary physical
theories or theories of the brain they
always have an encoding bit and a
decoding bit and they kind of balance
out. So we've got at the end of the day
predictions we can test against data and
we can say this theory is right or
wrong. So that's roughly my viewpoint,
but there's a lot there. We're getting
into deep water. Yeah. Yeah.
Thanks, Robert. We we've also of course
emailed on this, but external
information is required to interpret
those physical events as a computation.
So I think I'm 100% with you on
relational seiosis and the idea that
multiple perspectives could be taken on
a computational process. But what causal
relevance other than actually
intervening on the internal states would
those external states have? So those
interpretations matter for the
interpreter, but but unless they reenter
causally into the target system, how do
they come to matter for the system
itself?
Well, I think that's what I'm going to
address on the second half of of the
talk.
Um and and again you know the whole
picture is the computer only picture is
radically incomplete and you get gaps
like that but there's something else
comes along which fills the gap and
that's what I'm going to talk
about.
Okay. So
uh that by the way we can come back to
that but that's more discussion. I
thought some people might object might
have that question which in a sense was
Carl's question that isn't every
physical thing a
computation and to a certain extent I
can regard lots of physical phenomena as
computation uh I can regard a gas in a
cylinder as a computation and there the
encoding is something that gives the gas
certain temperature the but my theory is
not just gas in a cylinder it's gas plus
a pressure piston which measure the
pressure and that the pressure piston is
what does the decoding. So that's a bit
of a diversion. I'd like to move on from
this slide because that's not what the
second half of the talks about. If
anyone wants to come back to this slide
later, I'm happy to do
so. Now what's the positive proposal?
How can brains be conscious?
The positive proposal is the brain is a
neural computer but it's not only
that something else is happening and it
has to be happening because we know
brains are conscious and so we need
something else to make them conscious.
So what might that something be? The
proposal here is that the the the extra
something is an analog model of
reality and and that an analog model is
different from what goes on in digital
computers or neural computers. So what's
an analog
model? Approach this by examples. A toy
car is an analog model of a real car or
a map is an analog model of a piece of
terrain or a photograph is an analog
model of some scene. So this gives us
some idea of what analog models are
about. And I claim we try
and encapsulate this in definition of
what is an analog model. An an a model M
is an analog model of some physical
situation P. If M has the same topology
as P. In other words, if the situation P
is donutshaped, then M is
donutshaped. And there's some kind of
pointto-point correspondence between the
physical situation P and the model M. So
uh a point in the model is a a function
of a point in the physical thing. And
the function f which relates points in
model and physical reality are a
continuous function. Uh mathematically
it's a fiber bundle I think and it
preserves
neighborhoods and it preserves spatial
binding. So there are things in the
analog model which are like borders for
instance borders on a map which are also
borders in the real situation. So some
of the information in the model
M in the physical situation P is
reproduced in the model M but with no
encoding. And so there's certain
information you can get out of the model
M which doesn't require decoding. And
that is I believe the secret to
consciousness that there is an analog
model inside the brain and that model is
a source of consciousness. that model
doesn't need any decoding. So there can
be information in
consciousness about external things
because it's gone into the analog model
without being encoded.
So um analog I should say that I've
tried to discuss analog models in a
couple of minutes but they're not that
simple because you could say analog
computation requires external decoding
just like any other form of computation
and that's what I believe also at said
and there's been loads of philosoph
philosophical debate about what analog
modeling is people like Gibson Foder and
Pelician and so on and you could say
Well, you've given the examples maps and
photographs, but they are actually
encoded. They are divisible. You look
very closely at a map, you can divide it
into
little fibers on the paper and they've
got ink or they haven't got ink. And the
ink is an encoding of information. Or
you look at a photographic film and
there are molecules of
dye. Or you look at a computer screen,
there are pixels. They all encoded.
However, those aren't the only examples
of analog models. There are other analog
models which aren't
divisible. For instance, if you have a
lens and the optical image is a model of
reality, but it is not divisible because
you zoom in very closely on the image,
you get to defraction limit and you just
get blurry. So, you cannot keep dividing
an image from a lens as far as you like.
Similarly, a hologram it's not divisible
because a hologram is a fer transform of
a spatial distribution on a film say and
so you can't zoom in as close as you'd
like on a hologram and keep dividing and
dividing it. And another exa more exotic
example is a single quantum state that's
not
divisible, notoriously not divisible.
And there are some quantum states which
can hold very large amounts of
information, microscopic amounts of
information and they last longer. They
last a long time. Most quantum states
get dissipated in 10us 18 seconds and
don't last at all. But certain quantum
states can last very long times and
these are Bose Einstein condensates.
They're things like superconductors or
super
fluids. By the way, if Fran is watching
this talk, I'm running out of water. So
if she could bring me some water, I'd be
very
grateful. Um, so Bzin and condensate an
example of quantum states which can
exist for a long time and can hold a lot
of information but they are very rare
states of matter. So they I think people
say that couldn't exist in the brain but
I think we shouldn't rule them out
because evolution is very clever. So the
question of analog representations in
the brain is still I think an open
question and it's a question of physics
or biohysics rather than a philosophical
mathematical
question.
Right? So what's this got to do with
consciousness? Analog models have
spatial binding. In other words, they
have things like boundaries which map to
boundaries in the real world.
Now, our conscious experience includes a
3D model of local space. That's what
it's like to be. You see a model of your
computer screen in front of you, model
of your table and so on. And that model
has spatial armor coming. That's
great. Thank you.
um that model has spatial spatial
binding and so that model could be the
source of consciousness with no decoding
required. So here is the positive
proposal that the brain as well as a
computer contains an analog model of
local
space and that analog model is the sole
course of source of consciousness is
consciousness is nothing to do with the
neurons in the brain. It's all coming
from that analog model.
So that's a positive proposal and I'll
sketch a bit. Um so the question you
might ask is well you've said there
might be an analog model of space in the
brain. What use would that be? Why would
it
evolve? Would it serve any purpose?
Would it help the brain do any real
computing that brains need to do? And
the answer is yes. It could be very
useful because it could store a basian
maximum likelihood model of what's going
on around the animal for limited periods
of time, say for a few
seconds. It could be the place where all
the sense data about the animal's
surroundings get integrated into a
single best likelihood
model. And it could persist this
information for a fraction of a second
while the animal decides what to do. It
could keep this information while the
animal classifies the things around it,
recognizing things that they have to do
things about. It could be used for
simulating and planning what the
animal's going to do. And it could be
used for comparing the present situation
with past situations like memory and
learning. So the answer is yes. There
could be lots of uses for an analog
model in the
brain. Could it happen? There is a
possible physical form for the model as
a wave exertation and I've written
papers about this but I'm not going to
divert into those papers now because
that is simply for the purposes of this
talk just an existent proof to prove
that it can be done it could be done if
evolution could use a wave excitation in
the brain to store information then that
could be where the analog model is
stored and just to illustrate that in
terms of free energies principle and
active inference. Um here is a picture
of the classic active inference FE model
of the brain. Brain is a neural computer
and it has a markoff blanket. There's
the out what I call had many markoff
blankets but has an outer markoff
blanket between the brain and the rest
of the
world and the sense organs are outside
them the markoff blanket. They encode
information which comes through the the
markoff blanket. The brain does
computation and then neural spike trains
come out of the markup blanket and they
go to muscles which turn into physical
action. So there is encoding and
decoding in this computer model of the
brain. But there's no decoding inside
the brain.
So active inference is all about this
cycle here where the muscle actions
produce all sorts of changes in the
world and they come back by a sense
organs. So active inference and the FE
is a very complete and capable model of
the brain but I would claim it cannot
give you consciousness because all the
information in here is encoded and
there's nothing inside the brain that
does the decoding. Decoding is done on
the way out.
So how would active inference and the FE
have to be modified to take account of
consciousness? It's as in this diagram
here. You have not only an outer mark of
you have the same senses and muscles and
the outer mark of blanket as you had
before. But also as well as the computer
in the brain, the gray computer we've
got here. We got the inner ring, the
inner right white right
ring which is the analog model of local
space. So what happens is the sense data
comes in is encoded the brain and then
it gets decoded again into this analog
model and from the analog model it gets
encoded and there's a rapid iteration of
comparing sense data with the model. So
that's the way the best possible model
of local space gets developed inside the
brain. And
similarly if the animal wants to plan
things then it extracts information from
the the analog model about the current
situation it does some computation about
it and it puts
back what the situation would be if the
animal made certain moves. So if the
animal wants to plan certain movements,
this green cycle here is what
happens. And so in this theory of
enhanced accurate inference if you like
there is an internal analog model as
well as the computer and consciousness
arises solely from that internal analog
model. The advantage of that is that if
you get consciousness from the analog
model, you don't need to decode
it. And the analog model is
just like what consciousness is just
like. So there's no decoding involved
and we've solved the problem which we
had with purely neural computer models
of the
brain. Okay. So that I think is a a a
future direction which I would hope
active inference would take in order to
produce a decent account of
consciousness and I think that's a
promising route.
So just to talk briefly about the future
for theories of consciousness. I think
some approaches most approaches to
theories of consciousness have this
brain as a computer only uh assumption
and therefore they can't actually
account for consciousness because they
don't have decoding. But I think some of
the theories do have some promising
elements in them. I think the global
workspace
theory
there it's compatible with the idea that
the global workspace could contain an
analog model of space somewhere in the
phalamo cortical system. Um certain
people have written Bjon Murker has
written about consciousness without a C.
Again this is compatible with the idea
that somewhere in the
midbrain possibly the phalamus um there
is an analog model.
uh I'll talk briefly on the projective
consciousness model which some of you
know very well and that says there is a
model of space in the brain which is a
projective transform model and although
the PCM doesn't talk about analog at all
it does talk of projective transform
model it has many properties in common
with our consciousness and I think that
is very much a step in the right
direction and I've got a a more deal
working out of this which I call the
projective wave model that says there is
an analog of space in the brain. It's in
the phalamus. It's in a wave excitation
or in insects it's in the in the central
body and that's the basis of
consciousness. But that is not really
the main point of this talk is to talk
about the future is to say we need to go
in some different direction because the
ordinary computational theories of
consciousness are not going to happen.
So that is really the end of um what I
have to say
um after 35 how long? No, an hour. Um so
open for discussion. Here are a few
questions. Is there any alternative to
having an analog model in the brain? Is
there some other thing that could be the
cause of
consciousness? Could it be stored in
neurons or does it have to be stored in
some other form such as a
wave? And I think this has not only
implications for consciousness but also
implication for cognitive models of the
brain. If we admit this possibility,
does that actually help us produce
models of how the brain works or
alternatively should we just give up on
theories of
consciousness? So um open for
questions. May I jump in? Sure.
[Music]
So, one
thing just a sec. I'm going to close my
door because there's people here.
All right.
So one thing to bear in mind with
respect to this discussion about the
brain in particular is that for most
neurohysiologists, brain scientists, not
cognitive brain scientists as you know
who often so are not real
neuroscientists
uh have said and restated when after
computers and in
their digital uh form. So with this
encoding and decoding process involved
have emerged that the brain is not a
computer in the sense that precisely the
brain is an analog machine that neuron
do not encode things that actually spike
strains are analog signals. So it's
actually the core belief of the
classical
neurohysiology and computer sorry brain
scientist uh that the brain is not
digital but an analog machine that has
analog model of the world. Now in the
detail how that would work and how that
would generate phenomenology as the
subjective experience we have is I guess
another question. Um so I think that is
very what you are stating is actually
very classical from the perspective of
neuroscience but it has been forgotten
uh by a lot of people who are in the
business of cognitive neuroscience and
you know and myself at some point I
thought you know we have to go back to
the analogy computer of between mind and
brain and software and hardware. So
entailing some sort of encoding decoding
through virtualization but that's a
theory of mine that you know I don't
know what I believe today but actually
what you say is about you know can the
can the brain be considered or part of
the brain or neurons can encode analog
model for most neurohysiologists that's
already the case uh how is another
question so now in term of the
particular model and implementation or
form of this analog model I would even
go further and say at this point in my
career and reflection where I I'm
actually completely lost uh I'm open to
anything including what I used to
consider as sort of science like the
claims of chmer about quantum mechanics
why not and even some other physics that
we don't even know yet and haven't
understood in term of you know the brain
maybe like Okay, I'm going to use an
analogy like an antenna of source
receiver and emitter that connects to a
physics in which you know consciousness
resides that we may never understood. So
the field is open for me and uh I'm I'm
not shocked by your arguments. I think
it's worthwhile to pursue.
uh but I don't have a definite answer
neither of what it could be this analog
model or even if there is not a physics
in which encoding and decoding can
perfectly make sense.
Okay. I I I've got two remarks. I
suppose I I mean I Well, one let me
remember one of them. The idea that the
brain is an analog computer and neuron
spike trains are an analog
representation of reality. I don't think
that to be spike trains are
irretrievably encoded and we don't know
how they're encoded. We we don't know
and we certain neurons parameter neurons
maybe firing rate is is the way to look
at it but even looking at firing rates
is decoding
but nobody in neurohysiology look as at
firing rate
uh uh in a computational sense of the
term as computational neuroscientists do
they just consider it's an analog signal
that has an analog relationships with
the amount of neurotrans transmitter
that are going to be released and how
that's going to affect based on the
biochemistry of the synaptic clft uh uh
the potential of membrane on on other
neurons. So for them it's really like an
electronic machine of a classical analog
uh you know there is no analog digital
converter if you wish in the sense of of
a decoding of analog signal for them
it's all analog
I I suppose the other problem I have
with that is you can look at certain
neurons in the brain and and it appears
that they encode things or they
represent things by firing rate and you
could say that is analog but actually
how do you models. I'm sorry to cut you
Robert's the enthusiasm of the
discussion, but those are models that
have been extracted and designed by
people who started thinking
computationally about the brain. And we
had a fairly uh uh superficial culture
about neurons and neuro and
electrphysiology I would say for many of
them. And that decided to interpret
spike trains and their frequency or the
rate of spiking as a signal that in
itself was the meaningful signals in
their simplified model of neurohysiology
to be able to compute certain functions
like doing arithmetics or understand
certain basic memory mechanism and input
output relationships through transfer
function. But that's a small very small
part of neuroscience. That's the
computational neuroscientists that were
trying to do modeling and that
interpreted spike train as a relevant
parameter. But a true neurohysiologist
would never think that way.
You mean experimental neuro physiologist
or even theoretical I mean an
electrophysiologist who masters the
bioysics of of membranes of active
conduction that's a physical that way.
They think that Yeah. I'm talking about
people who worry about consciousness.
Yeah. But they are not they are usually
not real brain scientists. That's what
I'm saying. Yeah.
Okay. Uh Kenneth and then Paul or anyone
else who hasn't spoken.
Benmute Kenneth.
Sorry. just to u make a quick remark uh
with relation to what David just said. I
mean I think McCullik and and Pitts knew
their
neurohysiology pretty well and they knew
they were making a a massive
simplification and those indeed. Yeah.
Yeah. Uh making a choice and kind of
setting up neural network modeling, you
know, as computational. Um I just want
to say and it's also kind of following
up with what Debbie says. Um well I have
two questions really.
Um so one is suppose there is this
analog model. Um I mean can't we raise
the same sort of
objections to computational models that
we I mean can we couldn't we raise to
analog models the same sort of
objections we're raising to
computational models. So for example, if
you take analog computers like the
differential engine um you know Charles
Babage's wasn't it called the
differential engine that
that was that was Leon Babage. Well he
he did the differential engine and there
was a later one in the 30s. Okay. So
it's it's using ears if I'm not mistaken
to do Sure. You you mentioned the
abacus. I mean in it's an analog divi
and someone might kind of push and go
well really digital computers are all
implemented in an analog world so really
they're analog and I know there's like
the flip side where everybody's trying
to turn everything in everything analog
into something digital like you know
information ontologies or it it from bit
kind of uh so there's this kind to to me
the the key distinguishing factor is
that some of the information in an
analog
model doesn't need decoding. Okay. And I
can I can uh I can I like that idea
because I think that there's So then
that leads me to my second question. I
mean I like the idea because I I'm one
of those who thinks that consciousness
is not exhausted by intentionality. And
what I mean by that is yes, there's the
intentional level where you think like
you're seeing something as something,
but there's also the level at which
you're just seeing if we're talking
about for example. So for example, if
you you might wake up in the morning and
have like a a watted sheet in front of
your face and for a second you don't
know what it is, but there's still
before you interpret before you
interpret it. Right? So there's still
something you're sort of directly aware
of that doesn't require any decoding to
be aware of it. And then there's this
further layer of decoding which is like
oh it's sheet or oh it's kind of
perceptual and that's where
intentionality enter or meaning in the
sense we've been talking about it enters
in. Um, now, okay, so I like that idea,
uh, that an analog model might give you
that layer that isn't a m it's
information that doesn't have to be
decoded because it's really sort of just
built into the structure of that
uh, episode or that phase of
consciousness itself.
But my question for you really is what
is it to decode or interpret or
intentionally animate as a to use a
Huserian language like what is it to see
something as something that's like a a
further process uh you can imagine in
theory anyway a kind of consciousness
that doesn't do it that is basically
just kind of locked in this you know it
doesn't really sort of get outside of
itself.
Um that complicated question. Your
arguments earlier on kind of depend on
consciousness always involving
intentionality or interpretation which
you know um I certainly a tempting
thought that it that it always does. I
can't say that it's false, but I wonder
like what is the theory of
interpretation or the theory of
intentionality? Well, do you need one
for your your
project? Um well, th this um I would say
in that moment you wake up before you've
interpreted your sense data as this is a
sheet.
Um there are things in your sensation
like a boundary between red and green.
Yeah. You know and and you're you're
aware of that boundary before you say oh
that's about my sheep. Yeah. And so
there is a a
pre-interpretation experience raw
experience and that quality of the raw
the what it is is like bit is what where
the analog model
represents has has a a nice fit to
consciousness. Analog model has got a
barrier between red and green and your
consciousness has that. And as for
classification and intentionality, when
you see something on the wall, you say,
"Oh, that's a fly."
That is built in by evolution that
animals have to take their sense data
and classify it into things they need to
do things about. That's a fly, I can eat
it, whatever. And that secondary
experience
of taking a piece of sense data,
classifying it as something is useful
for the animal, but it also involves the
conscious bit. But once the animal has
seen a fly as a fly, it doesn't quite
see the raw sensate. It it right mixes
the fly up with previous flies it's seen
in in his memory. And its current model
of reality involves not only the sense
data coming in, but all the flies it
seen before, but they're going to behave
that way and be edible or whatever it
may be. I can agree with that. But what
I wonder is is that
um you know the seeing as or the
interpretation is that do you also want
to you want to deny that that could be
computational? Correct. No. No, it's
computational but it feeds results back
into the model.
So you think that in classifying is when
I see a fly on the wall, there's
computation in my brain that says that's
a fly, but then that computation feeds
back into my analog model. So my analog
model is a bit more flyike than it was
before. But now you've got
intentionality in your computations. And
then we can go back and go, well, why
were you objecting to computations being
intentional in the first half of your
talk? No, my computation has evolved to
classify the visual field into useful
things that I need to know about. And
you know, it the computation doesn't
know that's a fly. The computation just
does some
grinding. And it makes my muscles do a
fly thing and it makes my conscious
awareness do a fly thing. But inside it,
the computation not aware of a fly.
Oh, okay. I All right. I'll have to
think about it. I'm not I'm not sure I
follow you completely, but Well, my
brain's evolved to classify things
usefully to help me survive. I agree
with that. Yeah. And it it that
evolution hasn't made it aware of what
the things are. It's
just for certain inputs, it produces
good outputs which make me avoid flies,
okay? Whatever it may be, but also it
produces outputs into the analog model
that says when I see a blur on the wall
and I'm not sure what it is, I suddenly
uh interpret that blur becomes a bit
more focused as a fly because I know
there are flies flies on that wall.
Okay. So the interpretation is a
consciousness is a conscious matter.
Yeah. No, the interpretation happens in
the computer bit, but the result of
being more flyike than a blower on the
wall is in the conscious
bit. Uh then it seems to me you're using
interpretation or decoding in one sense
in the first half of your talk and in
another sense right now. I don't know.
So I'm saying that the decoding happens
on in the brain has enc the computer
brain has encoded stuff in it and
there's two kinds of decoding. There's
decoding going out the muscles and
there's decoding going into the analog
model
at at some point if you wish can for
what I understand there is a decoding
that comes from the processing of the
within the brain that in on involved
initially a form of encoding that remaps
somehow this code into an analog model
that maps the outside world in a manner
that is uh coherent in term of shape if
you wish. So there's a shape outside the
world you don't see directly you encode
it through neural process and somewhere
somehow through some mechanisms to be
defined you it's decoded within to
generate and synthesize a analog
experience of the world for which even
though there is an indirect process
there is a onetoone of sort mapping or
some mapping that is more analogous in
the sense of continuous deformation if I
Yeah, but but this the same kind of
decoding that can happen when you ask
chat GBT a question and it spits out an
answer, right? No, it just does
electronics. What's that? Chat GPT just
does electronics, nothing else. Yeah, I
got you. But we're talking about the the
you want to say there is still a
computational sense of encoding and
decoding. Yes. But but earlier in the
talk it was about there's really no
computation without some external
observer sort of attributing or inter
interpreting a computation. Right. I'm
totally fine with your model. Yeah. And
that's the role of the analog model if I
understand where I'm trying to get.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So there's a kind of
there's sensory inputs. they get encoded
and then there's a
decoding step from the sensory inputs to
the anal into the analog model and when
and the analog model is like the
conscious episode and it's what we might
call the conscious interpretation.
That's right. Yeah. I go back to this
diagram if if you like. Uh I'll just
come back to
um is that diagram showing?
Yeah. But earlier you said decoding was
going to be the same as interpretation.
And so what I'm getting at is like the D
like for your your your set your outer D
to muscles. Is that really
interpretation?
No. But again I think from the they are
decoding spike trains. They interpreting
spy trains as physical movements. Yeah.
From the outset, Robert said if you only
take the computer model which in the
digital world exclud an analog model.
Yeah. In this rational then you cannot
get an interpreter that is inside the
brain. It's always some human or some
other type of interpreter outside. Yeah.
Now what he's introducing is a new
mechanism that is still to be uncovered
in term of its physics or its
whatever in which a analog model is
actually working within the brain and
therefore is not digitally operating as
in a computer. So there is a mixed
architecture between an digital and
analog system in the brain. Yeah. so to
speak.
Yes. But but just it just to it's it
seems to me like your your D and the red
box that process is not it the the
coding process is not itself an
intentional interpretation but it
results in one. Yeah. Uh it results in
one. Yeah. It's creating the analog
model. Okay.
Uh, Benjamin and then Paul and then
anyone else who wants to add
more. Unmute
[Music]
Benjamin. Benjamin, unmute.
Apologies. Um, if I understand
correctly, um, and I'm sure you can
clarify this for me, there are, uh,
according to this projected wave theory
of consciousness, there are certain
things that are, uh, built in or baked
into the system, um, such as like, uh,
time pressure or, uh, time perception.
Um and uh are there other things besides
you know uh time and space that are
would be necessary for this uh for
consciousness consciousness to emerge or
uh is it just that with you know the
effects of entropy?
I would put the emphasis on space. The
animal model is a model of space in the
present moment. And I think for most
animals, the present moment is all that
exists. They don't have a sense of
chronological time and they don't worry
about time. They're just worrying about
what they're going to do right now. And
so that's for that they need analog
model of space. So I I would put much
more emphasis on space than time. I
think chronological time is a recent
human thing and it came along with
language.
Great. Thank you,
Briana. Then Paul or anyone else?
Hi.
Um, so what if I look at something and I
can't quite comprehend it? Would that
that mean I'm not conscious of I'm not
currently conscious? What if an animal
can't comprehend something and
um or anything for that matter?
Sorry, I I didn't catch all the
questions. Then try again. So the
ability to extract meaning in an analog
model is what you would say is required
for consciousness then. Yeah. So what if
I'm unable to extract meaning about
something? Am I not conscious in that
moment?
No. I think you were asking about
animals. Um I think we got a perfectly
good theory of animals. paranormal
brains
um absorb sense data and classify sense
data into situations they need to do
things about and do things about those
situations that that theory doesn't tell
us how animal brains are conscious
um and that's so I would decouple the
two issues of you know how a brain does
its practical job of helping the animal
or the person survive versus how a brain
actually creates consciousness Now, we
don't know whether animals are
conscious, but we I would guess that
they are. So, if they're unable to make
the um make the classification of, for
example, the sheep from the Eural
analogy, then they would not be
conscious.
Well, I think the two questions are
independent. The animal brain can make
the classifications it has to um but it
it can do that without being conscious
of them.
Okay, perhaps Brianna, you can think of
an example that comes from
neurossychology. Think about a persons
to get dementia or some other very um
debilitating neurological
disease and for whom at some points
everything is a confused world.
uh who is very difficult to interpret,
very disorienting uh very minimalistic
in term of the content of the quantity
of information that the person can
integrate but nevertheless the person
still is trapped into this confused uh
and disorienting experience. So there
might be consciousness but not
necessarily very informative in the
sense of a coupling adaptive coupling
with the the world so to speak. Would
you agree with that Robert?
I I I I agree that that that that if you
take this
viewpoint, you can bounce it off all
sorts of situations like that that the
sort of person who's terminally confused
or or and so on. And I think you you
keep getting insights as to how the
picture works in those cases. And it it
it takes to me quite a lot of sort of
reflecting about what this model of the
brain actually means and how it how it
affects how we interpret various strange
conditions like that. Yeah, I agree.
It's instructive to do, but I I don't
have all the answers to what what comes
out of asking those questions. So the
patient with dementia would be less
conscious than the than someone with
that is. What would what we would denote
from that? No, a person with dementia
might still be very conscious of the
room around them
instantaneous way rather like an animal
has no sense of the future or the past
or causality or whatever. It could be
just conscious of sensations in the
present moment. Yeah. And for me, you
know, Brianna, what you say is somewhat
what would
the integrated information theory would
claims that you need to have some some
sort of complexity and efficiently
integrated information that is both rich
and synthetic to get you know a quant
high quantity of consciousness.
uh but to me u the core of consciousness
is not that and I worked a lot with
patient a long time ago with in
psychology
and I think you can be acutely conscious
while being totally confused. It can be
a very intense conscious experience to
be totally confused.
that it's not it's not it's not
informative in the sense of adaptive
coupling but that's a yeah so then
meaning is not required for
consciousness
or maybe a bit of meaning but at least
some uh uh that and again that begs the
question of what we call meaning it's a
complicated question but the at least
the structured adaptive highly
informative content of consciousness
when the brain is super efficient and
and well coupled with its
environment might not be what really is
the the most fundamental aspect of
consciousness. It often goes with it.
It's very useful to to have it. But I
remember patient is a very uh um amnesic
patient uh with interior amnesia that
were very very bad uh or dementia
patient that really really really were
confused but were living very intense
and distressing experience. And I would
say that even though they could not
necessarily have a very
profound recursive thinking about their
own consciousness and all it is
perceived by others etc. Even though
they they would have a very hard time to
navigate even their immediate
environment uh their experience was
intense.
Yes, I definitely interpretation.
Fascinating.
Is it here?
Hi, Paul. Hi, Robert. I thought you'd be
disappointed if I didn't say something.
[Music]
So, here we go. Um, I'm also a little
disappointed you didn't credit me with
the Roombar example.
Didn't I didn't what? Didn't credit me
with the roomar. I didn't credit that.
The room example is due to Paul.
Um so first of all just to say that I
I'm a lay person in all of the aspects
of um of this discussion except for the
fact I'm a professional human being um
and uh Robert and I often engage in
philosophical and um computational
discussions um around the area this area
um and
[Music]
uh not being a lay person I I can post
and questions, but I may not understand
your answers. So, I'm going to say that
right now. Nor may I.
Um, but Robert's requirement for
encoding and decoding
[Music]
um relies on the requirement for an
extra layer of significance and meaning
to use the word that he has given it. Um
and my understanding is
that those requirements for extra
significance and meaning come from the
fact that we know we are conscious that
we have consciousness. Um so Robert and
I in one of our discussions came to a
bit of an impass where he said well I
know the I can I can take the roomar
apart and I can see how it works. Um
uh and it's clearly just a matter of
physics and electronics. Um and uh so we
have that evidence and then we have the
evidence that we are conscious. He said
then he said at least I'm conscious. Do
you not know that you are Paul? And I I
don't
no I don't know I'm conscious in the
sense
that there is a clear category
difference between what I experience
what I feel if you like and what I can
imagine an
advanced
AI self-evolving
computer with sensors, actuators, etc.
to have I I cannot hand on heart say
that I know where that divine line
comes.
So I would just like to posit that there
is no meaning
beyond what our
brains our neural
brains what their currency is what their
conclusion of our neural brains is.
There is no meaning beyond that
because both the advanced roomar
whatever or or
ourselves we we attach adequate
meaning to what we perceive to inhabit
the environment we're in. So I I would
question why there is a divide. It
requires encoding and decoding to
happen. Um I think in a nutshell that's
that's the essence of the argument which
which I've rehearsed with Robert before.
Yeah. Um let let me try and approach
that. I mean I'm concerned with doing
science. In order to do science I need
experimental
data. And if I'm going to do science
about
consciousness, I need experimental data
about consciousness. And I have got data
I claim that tells me I am
conscious. But I haven't got data that
tells me the Roomba is conscious. So the
question whether or not a rooma is
conscious
um I don't
feel it's justified to assume it is
conscious in any it's anything is like
to be a
rumba. I just don't see that's a problem
for my science if it's solely trying to
account for consciousness of things with
brains biological things. So in a sense
uh the question whether the rumor is
conscious or not is of less interest to
me just because I don't have data about
it but I think I do have data about me.
But that's not the challenge I'm putting
to you
Robert is well the challenge I'm putting
to you is in essence is whether there is
a distinction
between the sensory experience ability
to operate in its environment that a a
well that's a rumor and beyond sort of
advanced AI self- evvolving possibly
selfreplicating ating u with
improvements um robot between that and
what we are. So again, I'm challenging
the notion
that humans have some
categorical
[Music]
distinction sort of self-awareness,
awareness of our environment, which
which we call consciousness, which I
have a real problem with that word. Uh
which is different to that of an
advanced piece of electronics and um um
computing. So it's it's it's I'm not
challenging to you to say whether a
roomar is conscious or not. I'm
challenging you to identify a
distinction between the two because if
there is no distinction between the two.
The only distinction is I've got data
about me. I don't have data about a
roomar and I'm doing science. So I need
data.
But you've you the data you've ascribed
to yourself is consciousness that is
distinct from a machines. So I have data
that says there is something that is
like to be me. This is the Thomas Nagel
sense of consciousness that it is what
it is like and internally in my brain in
in my life there is something that that
is like to be alive. I don't have that
evidence about a room. So a room doesn't
worry
me because I'm trying to do science not
just philosophy. I'm using philosophy
for science if you like and and for my
scientific purposes I need data and the
only data on consciousness I've got is
data on consciousness in
people but so I'm deliberately
restricting my focus if you like just to
do this and not that but what you're
saying is
that you have is that your consciousness
is putting a degree of significance on
the objects which your eyes light
on which is greater than that simply
required to operate in your environment.
Um I I don't I don't see Yeah. I mean
it's a remarkable fact. I I could be a
zombie but I'm not
right. Well that's what I'm trying to in
the pollightest possible way. Yeah. I I
mean you're only as clever as it's a
philosophical possibility that I am a
zombie but I happen to have first person
experience which says I'm not a zombie
whereas a rooma could well be a zombie
and I think it actually is a zombie but
it doesn't bother me. I just restrict my
viewoint to where I've got data.
I'm not sure that's what Paul is talking
about, but uh No, I probably got it
wrong. I'm saying my my viewpoint is
restricted. I'm only trying to do
science. I'm not trying to evaluate
philosophical
possibilities. I'm only trying to
produce a scientific account of
consciousness. And the only
consciousness I know about is what
happens in biological things such as me.
Yeah. And I'm not making a philosophical
point. I'm simply saying that your
requirement for encoding and decoding is
only
there because you think that this that
there is something there's something
some attachment of meaning and
significance required to those things
over and above what is simply required
to operate in an environment like a room
and I I don't I don't see that. I don't
see that.
Yeah. I mean, part of the confusion in
these debates is
that we're stuck with language and
language is encoded and it's encoded
very badly and ambiguously and we use
words with very different meanings. And
so we can construct all
these constructs about consciousness
which go way beyond the thing
itself and
which get us down blind alleys. I think
I think you know I have a a problem with
the term consciousness and it's it's it
it is one of those words that we're very
bad at. I mean we imag when we use words
we imagine they're kind of precise and
say what we mean but they are so
imprecise.
It does surprise me that the scientific
community would continue to use a word
like consciousness rather than breaking
it down to it consistent parts and
banning the use of the word
consciousness. It does not feel helpful.
That's been true.
Well, I think Briana had a had a
followup. Isn't that right? The Paul's
You are right. Okay, go ahead. So,
building on Paul's point, I'm actually
curious whether an AI model's need to
navigate its environment through
interacting with us and processing
tokens might lead to its own development
of a subjective experience. Um, could it
be that such operational requirements
foster an emergent intelligence that we
simply can't grasp because we don't
share the same kind of subjectivity? Um,
in other words, if these models engage
with the world in ways that parallel our
interactions, what exactly distinguishes
their processes from what we recognized
as human consciousness? And does this
experience involve extracted meaning?
I don't think I have a neat answer at
all to that really.
Um, I I just come back to my view that
anything that goes on inside an AI
computer, whether it's running a robot
or or anything else,
um, is not about
things. And I have consciousness, which
seems to me to be about
things. Well, for you, um, you can't I
mean, you can't verify that I'm
conscious or that no one else is
conscious. So why can't we verify that
um a machine is also um conscious?
And can they extract meaning like we do
from their own subjective experience?
And does that fit into your model?
If they are conscious, the consciousness
they have is not the subject I'm
studying.
Does that help at all? No, probably not.
That that does help actually.
That was a fascinating conversation.
Yep. How about each person can give sort
of a final round where where does this
take, Benjamin? And then continue
around.
Hello. Uh yeah. So I I to answer uh
questions about like um artificial
intelligence and consciousness. No, I
don't think artificial intelligence uh
can be conscious. at least not um
distributed systems uh specifically um
the needing diversity um
complexity these kind of things would u
prevent that from occurring the in in
any in any real like measurable way like
in terms of like subconscious or
something of that nature the the like a
thousand of a thing is not uh diversity
it's not complexity it's just But one
thing so in that regard I no I don't
think that it's can it's possible in any
way for artificial intelligence to u
achieve like sentience self-awareness
consciousness but it definitely looks
like it and I think that's pretty cool
certainly. So if it walks like a duck
and it talks like a duck it's probably a
duck. Yeah, exactly.
David and Kenneth.
Well, I'm I'm going to be a bit
mischievous. I agree with everybody and
I don't know at this point. So, the
everything is open to me or almost not
everything but I don't know.
Yeah, I think that is the last word
actually. Ken, well, I mean, I think
it's perfectly conceivable that you
could have a an AI that passes every
kind of souped-up touring test you want
and convent, you know, be they become
our best friends or whatever, and
they're complete zombies. I think that's
perfectly possible. uh at least it's
conceivable. Um on on the other hand, I
took your argument, Robert, to be
something like look, if all you've got
is computation,
um so if an AI, no matter how fancy it
is, no matter how behaviorally
equivalent it is to a conscious being,
if it all it's got is computation going
on, it's not conscious because we know
that these computations do not carry any
meaning. uh do not carry in
intentionality and consciousness at
least has the capacity for
intentionality and meaning. That whole
argument as we said earlier on is going
to depend on just like do you think
there is a reasonable theory of
intentionality that could be applied to
computational systems or natural
systems. And that of course is an old
debate as we as I said earlier that goes
back to even before Surl and Dennett.
But you know, sured and then people ar
you know, arguing about intentionality
and representation after that uh for and
then kind of you're right that chalmer's
kind of resuscitates it but the it's
also like it's a kind of a debate that
that um went somewhat silent I think
because everybody realize they have no
idea what to say um and at the end of
the day but I think it's you're it's
good that you're bringing it back up and
that you're making us think about this
in light of a new idea. Um, now that
idea itself, I want to ask you one sort
of last detail. Oh, let me just say in
in favor of the word keeping the word
consciousness. No, it's been tried
before to ban the word consciousness
from the philosophy of mind. This was a
very formidable attempt by none other
than the nefarious Martin
Haidiger with the word daine. And then
of course you just end up
replicating more ambiguity and you you
know so I think we got to pick some word
right consciousness is fraud it has an
interesting history but we got to pick
some word for it but okay let's let me
put that aside the the thing about your
your model is um this when you say that
this uh analog model of space has to be
topologically equivalent
to space ambient space is that right and
physical reality Yeah, you got a don in
front of you. Your muscle has a ton and
there's a a continuous function,
right? The the function relating them
must be continuous. Does that mean that
the analog model of space is itself
really just a space? It is in fact
itself a kind of space. And is it
continuous? And is it going to require
that the physical realization of it in
involves continuity? Well, in in in my
particular theory, the analog model is a
FIA
transform of a spatial distribution
which and consciousness somehow involves
a FIA transform but that gets technical
but nevertheless FIA transforms are very
deep in physics in quantum mechanics. So
I think for transforms having to do with
consciousness is not a big stretch.
That's a way of evading the question.
Yeah. Okay. Because because you you
might think no whatever is going on here
like when our experience of space it
cannot
be like actually realized in something
continuous or it can't no I think a a
real a miniature space inside the brain
is not going to happen cannot happen. We
know enough about the brains and that
there's not some miniature model of the
world inside the brain. Yeah. But I
think a fer transform in a wave is is
the way that can happen. Okay.
All right. Thank you very much. Thank
you to the live chatters also for their
vigorous commentary.
So thank you all. Till next time. All
right. Bye. Many thanks.